Guide to the Haymarket Affair Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Haymarket Trial Evidence, Dates 1883-86; Series I; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  - OTHER PAPERS SEIZED FROM DEFENDANTS
    - Drafts from Arbeiter-Zeitung Office
      - August Spies
        - "Die Shopschneider," holograph draft, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 20)
          Report on meeting of tailors and dressmakers union; accompanied by draft of separate article concerning tailors; also accompanied by FBA catalog card
      - Michael Schwab
        - "Die Kapitalistische Presse [...]," editorial notice, draft fragment, holograph, [1886 May 2] (Box 2, Folder 21)
          Appeared in "Editorielle Notizen," Arbeiter-Zeitung, 1886 May 3
        - Fragments of editorials, holograph drafts, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 22)
        - With unidentified author, fragments of editorials, holograph drafts, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - General
        - Unidentified author, fragments of editorials, holograph drafts, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 24)
        - "Briefkasten" and other text on versos of blank employer survey forms from the Central Labor Union, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 25)
          Most are Spies's holograph; employer survey form is in English
        - "Briefkasten," miscellaneous drafts, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 26)
          Most are Spies's holograph
        - Short news notices, manuscript drafts and clippings, corrected, [1886] (Box 2, Folder 27)
          Several are marked "A & K"; includes meeting notices and railroad timetable; accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Letters and postcards to the editors from various contributors, corrected, 1886 Apr, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 28)
          Accompanied by two FBA catalog cards
        - Arbeiter-Zeitung galley proofs, fragments, corrected, [1886 Apr-May]
        - Copy for The Alarm [?], draft fragments, manuscript, 1886 May 14, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 29)
          In English; page of editorial titled "Capitalist Programe," and classified ad for a rifle, annotated with names of witnesses for the prosecution
        - "Comrade Parsons was next introduced [...]," summary of Haymarket speeches of Parsons, Spies, and Fielding, clipping and manuscript, [1886 May 5] (Box 2, Folder 30)
          In English
    - Correspondence
      - August Spies
        - Chardon, A., to [August Spies?], [18]83 Jun 26 (Box 2, Folder 31)
          In French; accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Gorsuch, W. J., [18]84 Aug 21 (Box 2, Folder 32)
          Accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Kaas, Max von, [18]84 May 23 (Box 2, Folder 33)
        - Klaessig, Emil, [18]84 Feb 6 (Box 2, Folder 34)
        - Kaufmann, Joseph, 1884 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 35)
        - Kobitzsch, Rudolf, 1884 Nov 27 (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Malkow, Michael, 1883 Oct 22 (Box 2, Folder 37)
        - Malkow, Michael, [1883] Oct 26 (Box 2, Folder 38)
        - Most, Johann Joseph, [18]83 Jul 11 (Box 2, Folder 39)
          Accompanied by typescript translation and FBA catalog card
        - Most, Johann Joseph, 1883 Nov 8 (Box 2, Folder 40)
        - Most, Johann Joseph, 1884 Oct 2 (Box 2, Folder 41)
          Accompanied by 1886 manuscript translation by E. F. L. Gauss, annotated by the court; also accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Most, Johann Joseph, 1884 Oct 5 (Box 2, Folder 42)
          Written on verso of letter in English from John Swinton to "Friend Schwab" [Justus Schwab], 1884 Oct 3; accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Most, Johann Joseph, n.y. Oct 16 (Box 2, Folder 43)
        - Most, Johann Joseph, 188[4] Nov 8 (Box 2, Folder 44)
          Accompanied by 1886 manuscript translation by E. F. L. Gauss; also accompanied by envelope of State's Attorney's office, inscribed "Most's letters"; also accompanied by FBA catalog card
        - Wiedmann, Ed., 1885 Dec 25 (Box 2, Folder 45)
        - Wiedmann, Ed., 1886 Feb 1 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Other
        - [Bulian], Paul, to Adolph [Fischer], [1886] Apr 30 (Box 2, Folder 47)
        - Bulian, Paul, to [Anton] Hirschberger, n.y. Apr 26 (Box 2, Folder 48)
        - Holmes, Lizzie M., to Lucy Parsons, [1886] May 1 (Box 2, Folder 49)
        - Rhoades, J. Frank, to Albert Parsons, 1886 Jan 4 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous
      - "Fischer's Fulminating Cap", [1886] (Box 2, Folder 51)
        Accompanied by envelope of State's Attorney's office inscribed by JSG, and by fragments of English-language newspaper in which it was wrapped
      - "Deutsch-Amerikanische Typographia, Reisekarte für Adolph Fisher", 1883 Jun 6 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Membership cards for International Working People's Association and Lehr- und Wehr-Verein, 1883-86 (Box 2, Folder 53)
        Four cards for IWPA and one for Lehr- und Wehr-Verein; one for the American Group of the IWPA belonged to A. [Anton] Hirschberger; the others bear no name
      - "Quittingun," receipts for subscriptions to Vorbote, 188[?] (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - "Handwriting Snyder", [1885?] (Box 2, Folder 55)
        Single leaf of manuscript notes with dates followed by names and addresses, signed variously "A. Spies, sekt.", "Herman Bauer, Secy.", and "B. Rau, Secy."; also annotated by prosecutors; accompanied by envelope of State's Attorney's office inscribed "Handwriting Snyder"
  - NEWSPAPERS
    Arranged chronologically
    - Freiheit. Organ Der Revolutionären Sozialisten. New York, 1884 Sep 27
    - The Daily Inter Ocean. Chicago, 1885 Oct 12
      Article marked on p. 8, "The Lake Front," regarding a socialist meeting
    - Anarchist, Organ der Autonomen Gruppen der I.A.A.. Chicago, 1886 Apr 1
      Passage marked p. 3
    - Lucifer. The Light Bearer. Valley Falls, Kansas, 1886 May 7-Jun 4
    - The Oregon Alarm. Portland, 1886 Jun 12
      Article by "Lizzie M. Swank" [i.e. Lizzie M. Holmes] marked
    - The Chicago Herald, 1886 Jul 22-23
      Article, "Beer and Dynamite" marked in Jul 22 issue; both issues include trial testimony
    - The Daily Leader. Eau Claire, Wisconsin, 1886 Aug 1
      Inscribed "J. H. Young" on p. 2
- Papers of the State's Attorney's Office, 1886-87; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  The bulk of the material in Series II is notes and drafts of legal briefs prepared during the trial and in preparation for the appeal to the Illinois Supreme Court. These include Grinnell's notes on the arguments delivered by both sides in court during the trial and the appeal, typed transcripts of Ingham's arguments and Judge Gary's remarks before reading the sentences, and notes of citations supporting the arguments of both sides. The notes and citations used to prepare for the appeal mainly address the defense's arguments that the court deliberately packed the jury with individuals prejudiced against the defendants, and that the accused could not be tried as accessories when the principal had not been identified.
  Papers documenting the investigation include drafts of a letter to Albert Parsons's wife, Lucy E. Parsons, from a police spy during the period when Parsons was in hiding, and a letter to Chicago Chief of Police Frederick Ebersold from "Amalie Shönfelder and the others" in Portland, Oregon, claiming responsibility for throwing the bomb. The Schönfelder letter is accompanied by a letter from the Portland police, who matched the handwriting to a hotel guest signing himself "John Fure." The prosecution inscribed the envelope in which the letter was stored "Schnaubelt writing," a reference to the fugitive Rudolph Schnaubelt, who was thought to be the bombthrower.
  Also present in this series are printed versions of two briefs submitted to the Illinois Supreme Court: the Brief on the Facts prepared by the State, and the Abstract of Record prepared by Black, Salomon and Zeisler, and Swett.
  This series is organized into four subseries: Investigation, Trial (People vs. August Spies, et al.), Preparation for Appeal, and Appeal (August Spies, et al. vs. People)
  - INVESTIGATION
    - Police spy, drafts of report and letter, 1886 May 8, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
      Report on Metal Workers Union meeting, and drafts of a letter to Lucy Parsons
    - "Shönfelder, Amalie," a.k.a. "John Fure," letter to [Frederick] Ebersold, 1886 May 20 (Box 3, Folder 57)
      In German; accompanied by letter in English to Chicago Police Chief Ebersold from S. B. Parrish, Portland, Oregon Chief of Police, 1886 Jun 23; also accompanied by State's Attorney's envelope inscribed, "Schnaubelt writing"; also accompanied by typescript summary in English
    - [?], Henry, letter to [Edmund Furthmann?] regarding "poison in bombs", 1886 May 19 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      Addressed "My Dear Fuehrtmann!"; accompanied by two manuscript fragments and one clipping, in German
    - Sketch or map with names of defendants and other suspects, holograph manuscript, [1886] (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - TRIAL (PEOPLE VS. AUGUST SPIES, ET AL.)
    - "Witnesses", list, typescript, corrected and annotated, [1886] (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - "Argument of Geo. C. Ingham, Esq., on behalf of the State," typescript, corrected, 1886 Aug 13 (Box 3, Folder 61)
      Inscribed "States Atty /2/- copy"
    - "Argument of Mr. Ingham on the motion for a new trial, on October 6th, 1886," typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, 1886 Oct 6 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - ["Minutes on Motion on New Trial"], holograph notes, [1886 Oct] (Box 3, Folder 63)
      Notes on arguments by Black, Salomon, Zeisler, and Foster; final page on Ingram's argument (page 7, docketed by JSG on verso) removed by JSG to group of notes in folder 65; three unnumbered pages follow page 6, one titled "Closing Argument"
    - "Gary's Remarks to Anarchist before Sentence," typescript, [1886 Oct 9] (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - PREPARATION FOR APPEAL
    - "The Jury--History," holograph notes and citations concerning jury selection, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 65)
      Includes notes on Ingram's argument on the motion for a new trial and notes on cases cited in that argument
    - List and notes regarding specific jury challenges for this trial, holograph notes, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - List of individuals peremptorily excused by defendants' counsel, typescript, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 67)
      Accompanied by index to examination of jurors, typescript carbon, corrected, with holograph note on cover, "Compile so that I can say: Total peremptory by State - 52, Total peremptory by defts- [...]," etc.
    - "Cited by Defense," holograph notes regarding prosecution of accessories and jury selection, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - "Minutes of Authorities," holograph notes regarding points argued by defense, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Summary arguments under headings "The Jury," "Principal and Accessory," and "The Conspiracy," typescript, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 70)
      Citations listed for each point
    - "State vs. Spies et al. Citation of Authorities," drafts, holograph, typescript, and typescript carbon, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 71-73)
      Includes citations read by prosecution and defense
    - "Citations and Authorities in re Anarchists Cases," draft, typescript, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 74)
      Includes lengthy quotes from and summaries of cases regarding accessories and conspiracy; accompanied by typescript carbon of draft in folder 71
    - Citations regarding the right to bear arms, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Citations regarding Res Gestae, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - "Anarchist -Witnesses-", index to witness testimony volumes I-N, two copies, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, [1886-87] (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - APPEAL (AUGUST SPIES, ET AL. VS. PEOPLE)
    - Arguments made during appeal, holograph notes, [1887 Mar] (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Hunt, George, Julius S. Grinnell, et al., Brief on the Facts for Defendants in Error. Chicago: Barnard & Gunthorp, Law Printers, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      JSG autograph across cover
    - Black, W. P., and Solomon & Zeisler, Abstract of Record, Vol. I. Chicago: Barnard & Gunthorp, Law Printers, 1887 (Box 4, Folder 80)
- Personal Papers of Julius S. Grinnell, 1872-1901; Series III; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Series III. Personal Papers of Julius S. Grinnell includes documents, correspondence, and other papers documenting Grinnell's career. Documents include certificates admitting Grinnell to practice in the Illinois Courts and the U. S. Supreme Court, and his appointment as Judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County. Correspondence includes drafts of a letter to Illinois Governor Joseph Fifer in which Grinnell denies saying to Chicago Mayor Carter Harrison during the trial that he thought the evidence against Oscar Neebe insufficient to convict him. Also present are a letter from the editor of the Chicago Democrat proposing to nominate Grinnell for mayor in 1891, and a long letter from the Socialistic Labor Party refuting a lecture that Grinnell gave on protectionism and socialism in 1889.
  Other papers include a draft biographical statement about Judge Gary, and numerous clippings documenting Grinnell's career following the Haymarket trial and his social prominence in the 1890s. Also present are obituary notices for George Ingham. While the bulk of clippings were collected by Grinnell via a press cutting service, two clippings postdate his death.
  Series III is organized into three subseries: Documents, Correspondence, and Other Papers.
  - DOCUMENTS
    - Admission certificates, District Court and Circuit Court of the United States of America, Northern District of Illinois, 1872 Nov 18 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Certificate of commission as Judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County, State of Illinois, 1887 Sep 10
    - Admission certificate, the Supreme Court of the United States of America, 1887 Oct 26
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Members of the American Section of the Socialistic Labor Party, to JSG, manuscript, 1889 Mar 17 (Box 5, Folder 82)
      Docketed "Answer to lecture on socialism"
    - JSG to Joseph W. Fifer, Governor of Illinois, typescript, corrected, 1890 Jan 17 (Box 5, Folder 83)
      Signed draft docketed "Neebe Letter to Governor" and cut into pieces; accompanied by manuscript draft fragments
    - Rardin, J. K., to JSG, 1891 Jan 10 (Box 5, Folder 84)
      Accompanied by clipping from The Chicago Democrat
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - "Judge Gary," biographical sketch, typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - "Mrs. Cushing on Altgeld," poem or song lyrics, typescript, [ca. 1893] (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Macaulay, Thomas Babington Macaulay, Baron, letter to H. S. Randall, 1857 May 3, copy, typescript, corrected (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Press cuttings regarding JSG, 1889-1901 (Box 5, Folder 88-90)
      Accompanied by envelopes from Bureau of Press Clippings
    - Obituary notices for George C. Ingham, 1891 Feb-Mar
      Accompanied by envelope from Bureau of Press Clippings
    - Metal strongbox, "Julius S. Grinnell. Private" inscribed on lid, n.d.
- Printed Ephemera, [ca. 1878]-1893; Series IV; 0.21; (.5 box)
  Series IV. Printed Ephemera contains broadsides, leaflets, and pamphlets of and concerning the labor and socialist movements of the day, most of them directly related to the Haymarket affair. They date from circa 1878 to 1893, and include Albert Parsons's "Appeal to the People of America;" a copy of the anarchists' speeches in court autographed by Parsons; Dyer Lum's history of the trial; a broadside calling workers to a meeting in New York the day the Haymarket trial jury delivered its verdict; and Governor Altgeld's Reasons for Pardoning Fielden, Neebe, and Schwab; as well as the constitution and bylaws of Lehr- und Wehr-Verein of Chicago and several pamphlets on socialism and anarchy.
  This series contains at least one item that Adams purchased separately from the Grinnell papers. This is a broadside published by the Federation of Trades Unions in September 1887, accompanied by an invoice dated nearly a decade after Adams acquired Grinnell's papers. At least two items in this series likely belonged to Grinnell: a copy of M. M. Trumbull's review of the Haymarket trial, The Trial of the Judgement, which bears Grinnell's autograph, and a leaflet entitled "What is Anarchy," in which a passage criticizing Grinnell is marked. The other items could conceivably have been Grinnell's, perhaps used for research during the trial or for his lectures on socialism in the years that followed.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - "Constitution und Nebengesetze des Lehr- und Wehrverein von Chicago," booklet, [ca. 1878] (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Starkweather, A. J., and S. Robert Wilson, Evolution or Revolution; Being a Brief Statement on the Doctrines and Philosophy of Socialism. San Francisco: Truth Publishing and Printing Company, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 92)
    Annotated in pencil throughout
  - Gorsuch, W. J., Revolt! An American to Americans. Allegheny, PA: IWPA Group No. 1, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - "To the Workmen. / An die Arbeiter Chicago's!", broadside published by Central Labor Union of Chicago, [ca. 1886] (Box 5, Folder 94)
    In English and German
  - Ely, Richard T., French and German Socialism in Modern Times. New York: Harper & Brothers, 1886 May 14 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - "Notice! Grand Mass-Meeting on Friday, August 20th 1886 [...] at Irving Hall" [New York], broadside, 1886 Aug 20 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    In English and German; published by "The Committee"
  - The Accused and the Accusers: the Famous Speeches of the Eight Chicago Anarchists in Court. Chicago: Socialistic Publishing Society, [1887] (Box 5, Folder 97)
    Autographed by Albert Parsons; text of Parsons's speech corrected in pencil
  - "An Das Arbeitende Volk der Vereinigten Staaten von Nordamerika!", broadside published by Federation of Trades Unions, 1887 Sep 18
    In German and English; accompanied by dealer's invoice to F. B. Adams, Jr., 1961 Aug 15, annotated by Adams; attached to album page with unrelated 1897 clipping on verso
  - "A. R. Parsons' Appeal to the People of America," broadside published by Lucy Parsons, 1887 Sep (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Lum, Dyer D., A Concise History of the Great Trial of the Chicago Anarchists in 1886. Chicago: Socialistic Publishing Company, [1887] (Box 6, Folder 99)
    Bound with The Accused and the Accusers: the Famous Speeches of the Eight Chicago Anarchists in Court. Chicago: Socialistic Publishing Society
  - "What is Anarchy? To the Public:", printed leaflet issued by "The Chicago Anarchists", [ca. 1888] (Box 6, Folder 100)
    Passage concerning JSG marked
  - "May 4th 1886 and November 11th, 87 / Zur Enthüllung des Heumarket- Denkmals," leaflet, [1889] (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Trumbull, M. M., The Trial of the Judgement. A Review of the Anarchist Case. Chicago: Geo. A. Schilling, 1890 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Altgeld, John P., Reasons for Pardoning Fielden, Neebe, and Schwab, [1893] (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Maul, J., photographs of Engel, Fielden, Lingg, Neebe, Parsons, and Schwab, cabinet cards (Box 6, Folder 104)
    Subjects' names in pencil on verso
- Other Papers, 1886; Series V; (1 item)
  Series V. contains one item, a letter to Lucy E. Parsons from an IWPA group in St. Louis in November 1886, inviting her to speak. This bears a price notation on the verso; that, and the unlikelihood of Grinnell coming into posession of such a letter, strongly indicates that Adams bought it separately to add to his Haymarket collection.
  - IWPA General Committee, St. Louis, Missouri, letter to Lucy Parsons, 1886 Nov 6 (Box 6, Folder 105)
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  - People's Exhibit 6. "Revenge! Workingmen, To Arms!!! / Rache! Rache! Abeiter, zu den Waffen!", broadside (in Series I), [1886 May 3] (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - People's Exhibit 32. Anarchist, Organ der Autonomen Gruppen der I. A. A., Chicago (in Series I), 1886 Jan 1 (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - People's Exhibit 45. The Alarm, Chicago (in Series I), 1885 Jun 27 (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Arbeiter-Zeitung galley proofs, fragments (in Series I), [1886 Apr-May] (Box Bsd, folder 109)
  - Freiheit. Organ Der Revolutionären Sozialisten. Newspaper, New York (in Series I), 1884 Sep 27 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - The Daily Inter Ocean. Newspaper, Chicago (in Series I), 1885 Oct 12 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Anarchist, Organ der Autonomen Gruppen der I.A.A.. Newspaper, Chicago (in Series I), 1886 Apr 1 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - Lucifer. The Light Bearer. Newspaper, Valley Falls, Kansas (in Series I), 1886 May 7-Jun 4 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - The Oregon Alarm. Newspaper, Portland (in Series I), 1886 Jun 12 (Box Bsd, folder 114)
  - The Chicago Herald. Newspaper (in Series I), 1886 Jul 22-23 (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - The Daily Leader. Newspaper, Eau Claire, Wisconsin (in Series I), 1886 Aug 1 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - Certificate of JSG's commission as Judge of the Circuit Court of Cook County, State of Illinois (in Series III), 1887 Sep 10 (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - Admission certificate for JSG to the Supreme Court of the United States of America (in Series III), 1887 Oct 26 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Obituary notices for George C. Ingham (in Series III), 1891 Feb-Mar (Box 7, Folder 119)
  - Metal strongbox, "Julius S. Grinnell. Private" inscribed on lid (in Series III), n.d. (Box Art, Folder 120)
  - "An Das Arbeitende Volk der Bereinigten Staaten von Nordamerika!", broadside published by Federation of Trades Unions (in Series IV), 1887 Sep 18 (Box 7, Folder 121)
- Restricted Fragile Material (Oversize)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 2, folder 30 (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Box 5, folder 84 (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Box 5, folder 88-89 (Box 8, Folder 124-131)
  - Box 5, folder 90 (Box 8, Folder 132)